Hi all good evening guys am I audible and visible great thank you to see so
we'll wait for five minutes until all people join meanwhile I'll share my screen do let me
know guys if you can see this screen share also okay it failed I'm not sure
why I'm not able to share the screen today isn't screen share working guys
are able to see VS code okay give me a second I'll join back the call okay just a second
I'm audible right again just trying to check on this I'm not sure let me take a screenshot
of this one screen share is failing and post it on a slack
give me a minute guys I'm just speaking tech team
let me retry again
sure starting the screen share but failing again
I'll try to rejoin guys give me a minute okay we'll start it anyways 905 let me restart the
I'll inspect this one
okay
guys give me a minute I'll check with the team like what we can do here because
technical issue not from my side
give me a minute guys I'll check on call
guys let me try
once again if not we might have to reschedule this class it's not in my
hand I'll try to rejoin it give me a second close the browser instance and
start again
guys let's try again
started working is it okay a minute guys just a minute I'll have to do some
of my setup
but screen share is working fine right just want to check with you guys once
right okay give me a minute guys okay fine yeah so how's everyone doing just
will get started in two minutes how's everyone doing this great so how's your
assignment going is everyone able to solve their assignments any challenges
from assignments perspective cool let's drop a message in group also whatsapp
group can anyone drop on behalf of me like we're getting started not sure if
some people have got dropped because of technical issue can anyone help me with
that
somebody's had a question somebody will check into that because we haven't
sent root dot js file but I'll pick it up in the doubt session okay thank you
guys thank you thank you all so I hope you all able are able to you know solve
the assignment problems that we like are you know said been given hardly I
believe one or two questions are there for each class and they just touch your
basics like refreshing your basics and but other than that thing right other
than that thing today we are formally ending introduction to like this two
modules I would say introduction but not completely and because we will be
dealing with these two topics each and every day but yeah but ease how you
feeling confident after like this seven classes that we spent on this like HTML
and CSS do you understand this one better right HTML and CSS guys I received
only one thumbs up we have good amount of people in class just you know are you
feeling comfortable with HTML CSS the concepts that we learned right if you
have any doubts if you have any doubts you know drop in the whatsapp chat or
ping me because on Saturday Sunday this weekend Saturday Sunday we are going to
have context or you can say exam on this content so it would be straightforward
basic and simple I would expect every one of you who have been attending
class at least you know you crack it easily because it's it's straightforward
and easy nothing included like there's no coding as such it's just a set of
rules right isn't it so keep or revise all the notes that we have shared with
you links just read through it once all the HTML and everything so be prepared
for this one once we add in class today right there is no class on Saturday
Saturday would be a holiday such that if you are starting or like prepping on
Saturday and taking exam on Sunday it's up to you if you're confident you can
so it's your choice so one request from my side would be surely attend
contest second thing keep your 100% PSP for assignments okay let's just not
overburden ourselves in future just keep let's keep this module clean okay are
you aligned with my idea guys
let's let's close off this weekend with HTML and CSS part okay now before going
into the today's topic like I just want to know are you comfortable with few
properties like all the properties related to font right and display
position when I say display guys I include all in line block in line block
then at least concept wise you should be okay because you haven't used it
that's okay up to an extent but whatever concepts I have taught you are those
clear and position when it comes to question I also have shared you a chart
that can be used for revising like if you go and see here in the self-study
and you open this you'll be able to see like all the five positions that would
act as a like shot of you know revision sort of thing right sticky static
absolute relative and then there is one what is the other one guys fixed right
and then we have discussed about box model right box model is really common
each every element in HTML is a box so we have by default like this is a
content area around that you have something called as padding and this
particular thing acts as a my border and then you have some space around it
called as margin right so I hope this all things are clear whatever CSS we
have learned and the HTML we have specifically talked about you know
tables forms and introduction to all those concepts right so I hope you revise
everything and then go ahead with us like all the assignments just go to the
assignments it's for your use case like going front ahead right once I start JS
then I go for react it would be really easy for you like if you know HTML CSS
and JS right this three to a good extent you can learn anything like react view
angular or you can have next year's or you can write n number of n number of
things but if you know only this three at good extent then only you can start
with them okay so having good understanding of this three things is
really important so we covered as a part of our club this two by today's class
content will be covered but we'll keep on practicing it so and I would I hope
that whatever we have learned together you will be revising them and being
like you'll be confident about them if you have doubts shoot at me I'll try to
help you out and understanding and solving them okay guys right now let's
let's get started with today's class okay you know by the heading you might
be seeing something called advanced CSS but not specifically advanced CSS I
would call it but it's a basic definitions and basic some of some more
properties okay let's explore something what was a full form of CSS guys does
anyone know this I haven't told it I guess till now anyone does know it does
anyone know it what is the full form of CSS cascading style shit
right we have used this word multiple times like when we are linking an
external styles file right whenever we are linking external style then we used
to give relation relation to that link as a style sheet so if we have came
across this word good amount of times but what is this word what is this word
okay what is cascading okay we'll explore that we'll explore what is
cascading before that anyone know anything on this what is cascading does
anyone know what cascading is all right good so we'll explore that but before
that I need your help to understand the basic difference between two things one
is called priority one is called specific okay so Ashwini had some
parent props to child firstly the props word is itself too complex to explain
now Ashwini so maybe we'll talk about that but I just want you guys to answer
me what do you understand by these two words what is priority and what is
specific when what are the use cases you see a priority what is the use cases of
UC specific how do you define these two things anyone
guys please come on quick okay I got Kiran says sequence what sequence
signify signifies Kiran what does it talk about
let's say this is a series of events isn't it
like what you should be doing an order of execution or you can say order of
execution right and the specific when you say when we say specific it's like
whatever modiji say that's a specific and it's final isn't it
other than promises but more digits words are like specific task particular
thing particular everything is fine
yeah he can say in a 500,000 bandhaj ratse so that's what he specific aborted
he declares it there is no priority order okay so but I hope you got the
basic understanding about these two words right priority and specific now
we'll understand these two things in terms of CSS actually let's go to the
and let's see actually and then we'll understand the word cascading also how
what is cascading and how does it work or how can you relate it because we have
seen that we have already discussed that one but we haven't connected that with
this you know jargon called cascading okay let's create a class 7 and let's
create an index.html file inside this again I'll initialize this one and let's
say what I'll do is that let's take a simple example firstly what I'll do is
like let's say I have a diff and just a diff inside that let's say I have a span
tag inside span let's say this is a para 1 okay next let's say I have a line
break here okay again I have a span let's say this is a para 2 and once this
div is ending let's say I have a div again here I have an h1 tag and let's
say this is a heading simple so what I'll do here is that while open a style
block here okay once I have style block let's say I give some diff I'm
selecting an element selector I'm selecting a diff then I'm directly
giving it as a color okay let's say and color would be tomato okay then also
what I'll do is like I'll select the span I'll give something color like
it's a dark blue okay and also again I'll select diff I'll make color as a
red no let me open preview here but I just want you to you know help me out
understanding what would be the colors of each thing would be let's say I add a
span again and I make color as tomato
grace
red and tomato okay so what should be going for red and what should be going
for tomato let's say this is one and two and three I add a three here now red
goes for a day find tomato for the span okay but I gave in context of span is
tomato okay then this h1 tag guys h1 tag what this h1 tag will go for what this
h1 tag will go for right okay now let's see if this is working if this is
working rightly no okay what's happening is let's let's change this color to bit
you know different so that you will be able to see a difference okay now what's
happening here is like para 1 para 2 we have given something like dodger blue
and we have something called we overrided with a different color now why
this sort of property is working firstly why this sort of property is working
like why we are able to override CSS okay so what CSS talks is like this is
like this is what we call it as cascading cascading is something like if
you say cascade whenever you see that cascade let's say that different what is
cascade let's see in the browser let me pull an instance of in a browser say I
say meaning of cascade okay so what it says you know pour downwards like if you
see in large quantity like cascading down the stairs pass something on a
succession to the other or small waterfall typically one of the several I
mean in general something which is coming down the line I mean like coming
from talk to bot is that clear now all the properties when we say overriding or
something is happening this is because that we say that in what CSS by
definition that rule applies is like so it executes on top to bottom but there
is a trick here let's say I give here style
and color blue okay this blue color is applied but what if what if I cut this
style what if I cut this style and paste it below here below the body what would
happen guys if I paste it below the body
do you think this blue tack will be updated do you think this blue tack will
be overridden no change right this this is something we have already discussed
in first class right the reason I'll tell you so how can you remember this
cascading how does it work is let's say surely it works from top to bottom that
point is clear top to bottom it will work but only one thing will have our
top priority which is called which is inline CSS inline CSS will have top
priority how does it work is let's say whatever element is there let's say this
is h1 okay for this h1 it will check by default if there is something like style
added it will pick it up this one and apply if there is no style added for
this element then it will go and see if there is something style that need to be
applied to this one but if there is directly available near to it it doesn't
go and try to find it that point is clear so it works from top to bottom but
it starts from this element here okay
is that clear guys like inline will have highest priority
actually I'll give you the logical explanation for this one why does this
happen in some time like let's say in 10 minutes but I see one thumbs down
Ankit you didn't you understand this inline when I say inline I mean to say
that this something that yeah when I mean to say inline it is something
whenever you define here inside the tag itself whatever attributes to define
here we say that inline like inline CSS I have explained this keyword in the
initial class right you have three types of CSS inline internal and external this
is something called inline whenever you define the style tag that is called as
internal and whenever you use link tag and separate style file then you call
it is called as external are you able to recall this one Ankit right great so I
hope the word cascading is clear now it just like which CSS should apply okay in
general it executes from top to bottom and it it overrides and clear the all
the conflicts exist and then there is H1 already blue doesn't matter if inline
style is applied that will you know be applied whatever cost it comes okay but
what if this is something we are saying in terms of priority right that hey if
there is a inline style it will be applied and it will like if there is no
style whatever you know after resolving conflicts whatever style comes it will
apply but what if there is a inline style already defined for the H1 let's
say style color it's red is given and there is some content okay but I want
this particular thing not to be applied but I want something else to override
this one I mean there is where this is place this is a place where we talk
about specific like can we override and specifically say that I want a
different style because when you go for a larger projects right there are too
many files or too many things that you will be reusing them and building them
okay it places let's say you define a one button and you will be reusing that
button again and again but if you but that button color will be different at
every place you have to override it but if someone when they define that button
they gave some inline style how would you override that button color how can
you say that specific like whatever the user story is does it doesn't matter
like our prime minister say something that's final he overrides everything
whatever is there doesn't matter right so that's how like how can you do it
specifically does anyone know how can you apply a specific okay Dheera says
not important keyword great okay no okay so if you see here what just happened
let me undo this one I'll put it this style block again onto the top just for
following this order that's look good ID class no all those things won't work
guys if you want to be specific you want to be updating let's say this is blue in
color span if I give something keyword like not important if I keep this keyword
not important do you see this blue style tag is also you know been overridden
do you say this this is like high command order you can say like how high
command does you know they gave this time how many of you watch that seller
like if they have stamp they don't stop right same thing this is a stamp of the
CSS that this will be applied at any cost if you go and see yeah I grown up
in Hyderabad so if you go and see here many times right if you go and yeah I'll
come back to that guys if you go and explore like any website you will be
able to see somewhere like not important being used at many places okay let me
explore one by one but generally whenever you want to override anything
you want to make it a specific doesn't matter what is the order what is
everything priority I don't care about priority I don't care about priority
whatever it can be but I want a specific style to be applied to this particular
element or this class or the ID whatever it can be any selector that you have
but if you want to apply any particular color to element for surely if you want
override it then you can use something called as not important and this is like
until unless you don't have a other way you're not supposed to use not
important because you will get you'll be flagged in your peers
but why we use keyword like it's like yeah Kabir you can say that the way I
remember is hey it's important whenever you say exclamatory mark you say that in
an action of you know amazed or shocked or like trying to stress how important
it is so that's how this works like when to use external libraries and want to
override their styles yeah right right something so company to get that point
like the just it says that hey it's like actually reverse order the way you can
remember is this way something that I relate is this way at least but that's
how syntax they have given like this one are able to relate like it's
important apply this okay so it's in reverse direction so guys I hope the
order of priority was a specific you are clear on this part like how does we
because we have already discussed like inline get highest priority then goes
with the flow from top to bottom if we when you use internal external doesn't
matter whatever comes later that will be overriding it isn't it but when it when
you wanted something to be specific you have to use this important keyword okay
so moving ahead guys moving ahead I'll take another example I want you I want
us some I will introduce some difficulty here this think of this one let me do
one thing I'll copy the example since it's a specific example simple example
let's say I have something called as this one okay an unordered list simple
unordered list where we are having three things apple mango and orange nothing
new right now I'll apply some styles to it okay well let me close this first I
don't want to show which thing will be applied and which not okay firstly what
I'll do is that I'll say that Li tag all the Li tags will have color red okay till
here there is no match I say that Li all the Li tags will have a red in color so
apple mango orange should be red in color but let's say now again I define
Li tag and I say color to be blue once I do it again so since we have just
discussed about cascading this Li will be overridden now all the things will be
converted into blue that is what we know but let's say if I make something like
this way let's say UL hashtag fruits so what I'm saying
select a UL tag which is having ID as a fruit okay then I'm saying select Li
having a class as favorite
okay then I'm giving some color as red okay then again again what I'm doing is
like I'm selecting UL hashtag fruits and I'm giving color as just think of it
take two minutes of your time think of it what color should be applied for
apple what color should apply for mango what color should apply for the orange
for the current knowledge that we have from the knowledge current knowledge we
have just think of it like what what can be applied just write it on some with
apple hyphen a mango hyphen orange hyphen that would be better for me to
you know take the mango goes for red okay okay let me write down here let me
give a comment here mangoes mango says red then I got answers as apple and
orange blue okay how many of you are agreeing with this one guys apple and
orange will have blue and mango goes with right okay let's let's explore this
yeah so if you see apple and orange are blue mango goes for it that's easy now
what if I make this one green
and let's say I make this one yellow I'm still not changing a class for mango
just think in terms of apple and orange
think of what would be the apple and orange apple will be apple and orange
yellow mango red okay cool so
yeah cool thank you guys so I hope you are able to relate with this one but
coming back to the right question let's say this I'll make it as a blue do you
see here do you see here difference between this anything here because if
you see here if we talk about cascading right if we talk about cascading first I
said all the light act should be in red right firstly how many of you are able
to understand logic clearly is there anyone who is still having you know
problem and figuring out this one okay now I just want to talk about these two
things here you say that you this one you will ally fruits both things are
common then you have ally and favorite you made it mango but you came back
again you said hey override all the ally tags inside the you will fruit by this
condition it should have been converted into all into this color right whatever
the green is being applied but that is not getting applied here did anyone have
this question
right so if you think from cascading perspective this is not following the
order there is something magic is happening firstly what happened behind
the scenes let's understand what happens behind the scenes okay whenever you have
one element let's say these are the one common elements and for this common
elements you kept you know keep providing a different isostyle using
different types of element selectors or different things but you kept applying
for those always you're trying to point at the ally here we are pointing ally
here you are pointing ally you are pointing ally here again a lie right you
kept trying to override again and again so when you are trying to do it this
way right there is something that happens here that's that is what while
resolving conflicts behind the scenes there is a tree called CISCOM is built
will come to that CISCOM tree in future but while it is built while it is trying
to resolve the conflicts and trying to say that which color should be applied
it follows some one rule specific rule called as a specificity rule now if I go
and hover over here can you see the something called a selector specificity
102 can you see this 102 and if I if I go up if I go up and apply here can you
see here what it is 1 1 2 ok now let's say I write down specificity here ok so
here specificity was something like 1 1 2 but when it comes to here let's say I
it was 102 now let's figure out where this is coming from where this is
coming from ok let's understand the specificity
ok we'll resolve all these doubts let me take this ok let's take that same
example ok what what was the selector what was the exact selector that we had
let's say I write down in the iPad I'll share back guys I have you will
Hashtag fruits Li now I want you to help me out with the what type of
selectors we have here firstly I want you to help me out with the type of
selectors we have here and number of selectors we have yes come on quick
what type of selectors we have here and how many selectors we have here inside
those types let's say what this you will and Eli is just think of this one what
is you will analyze
element right these are element I hope everyone have a better idea on this
this is element selector because they are directly HTML elements then what
type of selector is this ID right no if you see when I wrote down
specificity here now we have two elements and 180 this is what we told
now if you go here I have written something called as 102 ok let me say I
again write down 102 are you able to relate anything here what 102 is
standing for
what 102 is standing for guys right so when we say I'd one is something called
then zero is standing for class there are no class then two is standing for
elements let's do that same mathematical you know this one calculation on this
time something called as you will hashtag fruits and Li and favorite
let's do it for this one guys so how many again how many element selectors
you have how many element selectors you have in this example to what are those
you will and Eli again how many ID selectors you have one how many class
selector you have again one which is start favorite right that that is the
reason why you get this 112 which is ID then you have a class then you have
element okay so it went this calculation it went had with this calculation even
though cascading was being applied here it calculated specificity rule it
applies if you go and highlight the Li right if for everything for each and
every tag or which and every element whatever you do the specificity rule
applies for resolving the conflicts behind the scenes okay so when it went
ahead and tried it's it saw that the specificity is 112 and here the like
whatever we are when we are overriding through cascading it saw the specificity
is 102 now 112 is greater than 102 right isn't it you guys agree with this
pointedness that's the reason that's the reason though this particular mango is
being overridden but for that red was you know playing yeah not exactly
addition I'll come to that teacher but generally I'm trying to specify no I'll
come to that exact point but I'm just trying to explain why that red color
came in because the specificity of this particular color in red is higher than
compared to this one is this point clear like how why this kind of why this color
is being uploaded at least till now will come to specificity again anyone having
any challenge till now
okay great let's let's go and explore like it pointing to a specific path I'll
try to explain that Kishore then let's let's try to re-understand your point
okay now so what specificity says is that it has a generally four positions
okay let's say box one box two box three box four okay one two three four
now one first box goes further something called as thousands position and this
position is always applied for style or you can say in line style second
question which is called hundreds position is applied for ID okay hashtag
then third question goes for 10 which is goes for class then there is something
called once position which is applied for element selector okay what do we
exactly meant by this is whenever you are trying to apply anything like CSS
always specificity is calculated now if you see whenever we are seeing we are
seeing only in terms of this tree okay whenever we are seeing like two three
four we are only seeing for three things ID class and element because in line is
defined separately if you have by default anything like in line thousand is
always going to be greater than any anything that you define in the style
block or external styles are you able to relate now why in line style is give
gets more preferred so this is a logical explanation why in line gets priority
because there is while resolving conflict in specificity rule in line
style wherever you define a style block that's the for that thing specificity
let's go and see here in the example that we had okay this one here it didn't
apply I guess but here it starts highlighting but that's how it works in
line is always standing in thousands position okay now if you see this example
that we had if you see this example that we had the other example we had one
one two and then we had something like one zero two now even if I do this
calculation let's say one into ID being thousand hundred plus one into ten plus
one into one right I'll get something like one eleven but if I go and do a
calculation for this one I'll get one into hundred the zero into ten plus two
into one it's giving me one or two so one to well is always greater than one
zero two that's a reason why mango was applied red in color I able to get no
better understanding why that color is applied how it is calculated how why
like the styles are overriding or how it get resolved and why we say that in
line will have a highest priority compared to any other thing right so
generally while specificities this is how it is applied so I have some of the
you know exercises for you in order to try it out and explain it okay so let's
say I'll give you a five minutes let's take this example guys let's let's see
if you are able to solve this one let's say I have something called as test
thank you copy and then you have something called as h1 dot test then
something you called you have something called as try giving a really basic
example guys I hope you will be able to solve then I have something called h2 so
give me something here you know in the ascending order ascending order is
something like this if someone has problem no arrange this in the
specificity order take your time if anyone don't have notes or anything try
to calculate it let's let's just put those four boxes and try to calculate
each specificity and then try to figure out so that this is an exercise where
you'll get more confident about specificity
I'll wait for two minutes guys take your time until unless I get an answers so
Muneeshwar has suggested one answer Muneeshwar I just needed in ascending order
okay let's say Dheeraj is saying h2 then test then h1 dot test then hashtag
try and Muneeshwar like let's say if I count this way right three four now he's
saying that three is like hashtag try is less than h1 dot test three two then
one is dot test then four h2 yeah okay Muneeshwar let's say I again I would say
your answer and Dheeraj answer is same so I'll take it both so I got two options
guys so let's say this is option one this is option two this is for thumbs
up this is for thumbs down go and press it gets whichever you believe it is
right okay I see more of a thumbs up cool no worries so but I hope everyone
is able to relate this both are same now how come not same you sure I'm saying
h2 is greater I think it's they gave it a Vigneshwar has written in reverse
order but I would expect him also like have done it right okay Kabir go ahead
you type it down meanwhile what we'll do is like we'll write down specificity for
each one yes what would be specificity for this one dot test let's give
let's write down you know specificity for this one dot test give me in like
this way it is zero in line style 0 ID then I have one class then I have zero
element now let's go for dot test and try no not exactly no no Kabir it won't
be for dot test zero in line style zero ID H1 goes for element so we have one
then dot test go for class I have this one then I go for try have this one then
h2 0 0 0 1 okay coming to answer your question if I say dot test and dot try
hashtag try see try goes into the hundred question hundred and this is
ten so try will be always will be having more priority compared than dot test
is that clear yeah I'll share this one okay if you didn't note this
okay so I guess guys hope you got to understand this one then you get you
calculate it this is what the right order is I think Vigneshwar has also
written rightly but he might have messed up in the ascending and descending order
but that's also confused okay where hey how many of you have got clarity or is
anyone confused case if you are confused can you give me thumb down if anyone is
confused before confused not okay great so I hope everyone is feeling good on
this topic like specificity would be clear now so I would expect priority and
specific specific is something like going with not important and priority is
always something according to specificity calculation
okay and you can remember always this has a style then ID then class then
element this is the order like thousand hundred ten and one okay I hope now you
will be able to you know even if there you know sometime your CSS is not
applying though you have written right you will be able to relate with this
one cool guys so moving it to the next topic now is this one common topic which
jumps into most of the languages I thought like when I was start learning
initially right this topic wouldn't be there because firstly in my college when
I was in college I learned firstly Java like mainly people start with Java or C
plus was there you there you have object oriented programming isn't it and there's
one topic commonly in every object oriented programming right there's
something called as inheritance right everyone might have gone through the
inheritance topic it's someone new to programming language that's fine but I
thought this is specific to oops I am programming languages but turned out to
this one it present in CSS also no worries uncle no worries so that's a
something we have to we're going to start now inheritance topic itself but
let's start with basic guys basic like when I say literally yeah there's
something everything turned into blue do you feel that guys everything turned
into blue I mean it's happening everything in my system too much
technical issues no worries wear glasses I will highlight this one also I'll take
a screenshot that suddenly turned into blue
cool okay notice so yes let's let's get back to this one inheritance what would
be something like in general term like what would be the inheritance would be
where you might can where you can relate this property inheritance in general
terms you might be hearing at home and someone for not particularly from
computer science also might have gone through this word acquire property of
parents
right property or you can say ancestral property that you are getting by default
so whenever your children generational wealth hierarchy right so we'll learn
this topic again in JS also JavaScript oops okay JavaScript oops but let's
understand in terms of like how in CSS works okay no let's go and start with
examples because examples will drive you to understand in a better way let's go
there and open I have a list of set of examples that we'll be exploring it let
me make a folder here firstly specie okay I'll push this files inside this
then I make a new folder called as inheritance as I'm trying to maintain
this repo I hope you utilize this repo well for revision and practice purposes
okay let's say index one dot HTML HTML 5 then let's say I pull up first example
that I want to show you
no let's take this example guys you just told me parent properties by default you
get to the children and everything right now if you see what I've done there's
something parent if and there are something like children to it I've gave
parent some color right do you think children also should get that color
right we have seen this example already and we can say that yeah children should
have got this color isn't it so that's where by default this is a first step
where you can actually see that inheritance is applied okay this is
where the concept comes something like parent is having yeah by default
whatever parents is having children also get that property okay this example is
clear right I think no one would have any doubt in this basic one now let's
go and pick the other one
no let me open in the preview
no let's come and see this case if you see there is something like parent
today one if you go and see the day one color is red okay by default every child
in it let's say if I collapse this one okay there are the two child
specifically child one and child two okay so whatever parent by default
parent has it should go for every child isn't it that's what we try to
understand from the example one but now in the second example we try to see this
one that it second child also has a grandchild like I mean to say it has
its own respective chain and what we have done this the child one has having
a color green now it took it from like the this particular child the innermost
child took exam like color from this particular child everyone is everyone
able to relate this example that whatever I say what I'm trying to say is
that whenever you are going from this like you know spanning out whenever
you are spanning out from your current element you try to check for the each
parent whenever you go and try to check the first immediate parent if this but
that particular thing is having some color it will inherit from their
particular part it won't go to the till extent okay yeah so what I'm saying is
that let's say let's say there is a one grandparent okay he's carrying something
red color then there are two two child let's say this is a child one this is a
child by default this child one child two should be getting red but we said
that red C1 will have respect green color we just told this inside this C1
again there is a child call C1 dot C1 let's say this one now C1 even doesn't
have any property color so it goes and check with its parents do you have
anything now if we go and check here C1 has something green so this person will
take green and it will settle but it won't go and reach out grandparent yeah
child inherits a immediate parent try immediate parent is like not exactly
until unless if there is a something let's say what if it doesn't see one
doesn't have any color then it will go and check for the GP right so till that
property is found till till that property is found it will span out from
lower level to the top levels okay I hope this this this particular thing is
clear guys this example okay so now let's take an example of now this one
thing what if do you think if I have something like border if I have
something like border let's say I have something like border here one pixel
solid black do you see if border is being inherited by the other children
but does does child have border like we told parent have border by default
children are not having it right so there is a particular section of
properties which are by default inherited okay by default inherited what
all properties are there which can be by default inherited are one is for color
color is for sure okay this is not working let's say
color is for sure that is inherited also the properties with whatever font you
have something like font let's say if I give a font in the parent and I say
that font size I say 20 pixel do you say everything is being applied
so everything starts with font is inherited whereas properties with
something like you know border all like you can say box model properties okay
box model properties or display properties whichever are trying to help
you to enhance a particular thing right I mean changes view wise those
properties like position properties these properties are not doesn't work in
inheritance this point is clear like there are some set of properties works
for the inheritance there are some set of property doesn't work imagine if
border is working as inheritance each every element will be having border
that doesn't suit it right so that's how they built it now let's go and try to
explore the third example
let's say I have this
now let's explore this one guys if you see just now I have towards that border
once one px value blue do you think the child will have do you think child will
do you think child will have that border no right now and do you think child will
have color red do you think child will have color red yes right now then I have
used some property here called height has inherit let's say what if I comment
this firstly let's comment this if you say it is rendered as needed but there
are some properties yeah there are some properties with which you can inherit
forcefully there are some properties like let's say your grandfather properties
are there you want to inherit or there is someone else who want to claim those
properties they can they have an ability according to rule of law let's say and
for non-inheritable properties like the height is non-inheritable property but
we are trying to inherit for this child if you see when I've gave 100 pixel as
a height for the day one parent box is having 100 pixel let's say if I give the
background color so I give a background color of wheat if you see this
particular parent is having 100 pixel but children are not having rate is this
point clear firstly parent is having height and children are not having height
because it is non-inheritable but what I am saying is that I am using a
something like keyword height keyword height and I'm saying that inherit
whenever I'm inheriting it again goes like a color itself it goes to the
immediate parent then next parent and it sees that whether there is a height
property if there's height property please share it with me I want to
inherit please share it with me so here this particular child Dave one child is
having hundred pixel height let's say if I want to show you that height exists I
use something like let's say this one can you see this this child one starting
from here is having same hundred pixel height it's taking hundred pixel height
as parent there so if you want forcefully if you want to inherit a
property from a parent you can use a height and a property called inherit so
whenever you are going to a like there are some like let's say I write down the
definition here using inherit you can
get parent values for particular property
is that clear guys like how this is working inherit one anyone having any
challenge please please react did you all get it I see three thumbs down cool
notice now let's say going back to that
so height is a one diff I have given this diff as height hundred and height
is not inherited because I have added inside diff some content XYZ inside that
I have two children this has C1 and C2 by default since height 100 is not
applicable it just took inside the content wherever contains it just got
side on side of it itself what if I want the C1 to take the same height as a
parent I can say height and inherit whenever I say inherit it will go and
check with parent do you have height property applied to it if you have height
property can you give me that value as soon as it get its value it will take
that hundred pixel height starting from here it will consume hundred pixel then
something like this box will change as this parent content then child one will
have hundred pixel of height this is C1 this is P then under below this then you
will have something like C2 because that's what an order it is this is clear
okay this parent has a child yeah child one content is like top aligned right if
you want it to move below then you can apply display flex and yeah I think I
am Kabir pinged me personally then he corrected it did you get that Sambit I
hope this example is clear to you all like how you can use inherit okay then I
have another example let's say I go and
index 4 dot HTM
say when in the preview now if you see this guys we have created a simple day
for the content hello and we added background color and color red okay now
it's working fine but let's say if I go and create another day I'm having some
gibberish by default a black color is applied where this black color is coming
from why not any other color so by default whenever your CSS are loaded or
anything that you use it has a some default colors and default CSS are added
to each and every to remember something like this border and margin is not
removed like because body is having something if you go and do something
like body padding zero and margin zero
do you remember this body tag is by default coming and that's how for each
and every content that you write it or each and everything you do it yeah
yeah universal selector you can apply it for everything that's how else it will
work but now what I was talking about is that if you see this content it's
coming in black in color no this is what by default whatever default colors are
there whatever default browser gives you specifically if you want in any time
like any time in particular thing that if you are anything that you applied
CSS but you want to override with whatever browser is giving you like how
can you go for default thing like I want a default color to be there how can you
go and do that for that reason again what in inheritance like if you want to
inherit a default color you can always say something like get me an initial
color if you see around this keyword if I click enter now do you say this it is
div is converted into black color
so whichever thing are there if you want up default colors to come back to you
you can always type down wherever property are using it to the D like get
me the initial like if I go and select for the padding right get me the initial
padding there is no initial padding by default okay if I go and select that hey
get me the initial margin there's nothing there but what if I go and select
for the body it will be applied but I hope you got the basic idea when to go
for initial it's like whenever you want to go back and get the default colors
that are be given by the browser to you is this example clear guys is inherit
an initial property clear like we have discussed two properties okay let's say
I write on the this particular statement on the top if you want to remember
anytime by default whatever browser you are giving you are getting it from color
that will be applied or the CSS sensor okay next example would be index start
HTML okay this is one of the tricky example that I wanted to help you out
understand this property is something let me type it down so that I have added
too much content at their class let's say this is a dev with class dev let's
say content is hello now what I'll do is that I'll have a style block inside
this let's say I have HTML by default color red
okay let me open in the preview by default color is right now but what I
will do is that again I'll go and make a diff color as green okay then I'll go
and try to do this thing what I'll do is that let's say margin these are the
basic properties nothing use case here just 8 pixel margin then I'm trying to
define a new property for the color
there's something called as unset no by default do you see any difference here
when I use unset keyword here do you see any difference when I use unset okay
even if I if I comment this if you see this red is being imported okay so do
you see this this is working as inherit if I'm commenting this one it is trying
to import this one
this when I'm using color as a unset it is importing right it is like getting so
for whatever inheritance like capable things like color is in inheritance
capable and it is trying to get using answer so unset works in both ways
firstly on set works in both ways for
inherit table properties it works like
inherit keyword okay but for let's say non-inheritable
it works like initial okay now let's say I can show you an example of this one I
have let's say they have and everyone there okay I have multiple things have
defined it now if I use something like display okay let's say I go back now
what is the display of this property guys firstly what would be the like what
type of elements these are firstly are those in line or block level block right
so they're coming in each line now if I go and use something like a display
property let's say I make them here flex okay now if I use here unset what do you
think it should happen for non-inheritable it works like initial I've
just told you display is not in heritable I've just told you like
earlier now if I set an unset here and I save it do you see this is like
applying anything here firstly let me open this in the life so for better
understanding give me a second guys I'll pull this
no I'll go and select this one and I'll go and open this no if you see by
default when I'm setting as inherit sorry when I'm setting as unset if I go
for color property it is getting those color property and applying it when I'm
selling color equal to unset so it is working as inheritance like or like a
inherit keyword just I just just have a tool here written that line when in
inheritable properties it works like inherit get the parent property go and
whereas for the like properties which are like non-inheritable like where you
cannot inherit it like the property is here for display you cannot inherit it
so whatever by default browser provides you you'll get that property is that
clear because I've just told here unset I didn't say that get me a block here
is this clear guys like how unset works unset works in both ways like for like
initial and inherit but for this works for the different properties people get
confused in this I would say like I'll try to give an another example which is
combining all the things and I'll revise all of that stuff you don't need to
worry on this one if you are bit messed up here index six dot HTML let's say I
pull this no let's see this example is firstly let's try to figure out what
will be applied for which one now this is a question to you guys let's say I
have this stack here firstly a right and this one and this one and this one so we
have to guess what color will be applied for a lie what color will be applied for
anchor tank because there are two things like if you see if you go for the line
one the second default the color can have different color and link can have
different color so just think of it
what color would come to this one
let's just think for this a lie tag
default or the red color because it is trying to inherit because something
color is present for the body it will go and check for the ally do you have any
color applied no I'll go for you will tie I'll check there is no color then
I'll go for body and I'll see that in body red color is there so everything
should be red in color that's our guess right no when it comes to class one when
it comes to class one
when it comes to class this one second ally think of it guys think of it a
whole thing will be read or there will be something difference
see how like
aligned with that everything will be read cool think of third one
think of third one class two okay so a combination of two things are only one
thing whole will be black initial default fine in each whenever you see
that hey there is something like initial will be applied for this one but do you
see that I am applying only CSS for this anchor tag not for everything I am
applying CSS for only this thing in what this anchor tag color would be default
color whenever you write hyperlink
blue right so I we say that one thing will be surely blue and the other thing
guys other thing guys think of other thing like this initial and color this
keyword so we say that link will be blue in color but what's the use case of this
color initial and color what would be the color of this one both things
check what condition can be applied here black a light act content a lie it can
go and inherit right it can go and check to the parent no bodies having the red
do you think red does anyone think red
blue is applied for this part does anyone think red should be applied
but initial right but initial where I'm applying where I'm applying initial okay
let's see this so everyone says blues right okay then what should be working
for this use case guys what could be the use case of this one
when I'm setting as unset I'm setting as unset so we are applying for the color
color is something like which can inherit the property then it will be
red right now let me open this okay let's see how much our guess is right
guys do you see anything difference here so first answer is wrong firstly we told
that a light act content it will be able to inherit and get it but a link
whatever hyperlinks are there they don't inherit until you specifically
mention them because they are not in a table this tax itself whatever content
is there they act like a hyperlink they get some initial value for this one
default default link color is that clear this first one anchor tag doesn't get
like it doesn't go for inheritance property but the default and color these
two keywords like how if you're guys getting confused I'm not sure if
you're getting confused this is how it is guys parent then there is a child in
between the child can inherit or cannot inherit depending on the type of
property but default and color are of course inside content so this Li tag
anyways having a color right so that's why this color is up like this is line
one Li first line is clear no it's not it's inline elements like if I say span
let's say if I space span okay if I say span do you see this red color is being
applied Kabir it doesn't work with like all inline elements it just for hyperlink
the specific use case right now second example let's say we say that inherit
the property by default this inherit will anyways inherit then we told that
hey anchor tag can you inherit the property whichever parent is having by
this example dot class and a we say the inherit the property so it went and
checked body is having color right so it applied color right is that clear how
this thing is being applied you you all people just explained me this one right
so I believe we got correct on this one right then we had something called as
this one blue we all said that blue color will come but it happened like a
initial color content color what firstly I confused you here asking the question
what would the color of hyperlink but are we applying color on a hyperlink or
the content that's where it's a tricky guys but I I hope you all people got it
like it's actually black in color because few people all suggested black
what I try to stress like are you sure that okay
this is clear why black is coming yeah I'll post this on kid we'll take the
break okay this is black I say getting the initial color for this one now next
is completely red because unsaid works in a such a way like inherit property
when you're using on a color side of property right so I hope this example is
clear to you guys like how these properties are working how these are
rendering is anyone having any challenge over this and when understanding this
one so I hope every concept is now whatever we have understood those
things are clear if these things are clear we can take break guys any doubts
any doubts how many minutes you need guys eight minutes would work that's
enough right eight minutes
okay
we have like less amount of content to be covered next I'll try to cover that
let's take the break guys
which CSS Kabir like this one something that we have written the last one this
one okay so I'll keep switching the screens you can see this
you
well guys is everyone back
only one on this great thank you so guys I hope inheritance concept is clear to
you basically we have understood four five properties and then I have one of
the examples like if you does anyone remember like the cards example that we
built for flexbox and great right we but we have used one property right to show
it as a card likely we entered and some shadows around it box shadow right but
we didn't understand how box shadow box isn't it does anyone remember this so
let's let's explore that one property let's explore that one property so what
I'll do is that I'll I'll just use something like dev ID container okay
inside this let's say I click create do you hashtag card and let's say I'm
having a card here okay I render this one on the show preview now I'll
minimize this one and let's have some stylus style inside the style let's say
firstly for the container part I'll have some of the given information let's say
so I hope anything if you don't understand is any property don't
understand let me know like a given width like it should contain a half
width of this one then I got height of 200 pixel like this is the height of the
box then I have to like border should be two pixel solid gray like this is our
border then I gave border radius as 8 to make this as a curved edge right then I
gave display flex item and no and align items and justify content as a center
because to move this particular item into the center is this clear guys
anything that you feel you nothing right it's something that we have seen over
again again now let's come to the actual card okay so what we'll do is that I'll
give some width and height to the card let's say 100 100 pixel and height has a
hundred pixel and let's give some border border here okay one pixel solid
it's a black okay no others let's comment this don't need it also the card
is there fine let's have it no issues now I'll go and do something to the box
shadow no box shadow generally takes four things guys initially like let me
comment down firstly it takes like horizontal offset what does this exactly
means is that I'll show you increasing just let me write down this one
increasing shadow along x-axis or looking or consider horizontal similarly
next you have something called as a vertical offset okay then you have
something called as blur effect how much blur you need blurring the shadow like
then you have something called a spread till how much long how far you need the
spread okay now let's write down one one thing so the this goes in the same
sequence like let's say I go and say that hey give me one pixel or of
horizontal shadow two pixel or vertical shadow okay can you see this like I'm
not giving any other property let's say this only these two properties if I keep
on increasing this let's say if I give you five pixel can you see this in
horizontal direction the shadow is increasing if I give 15 this way on the
cross axis this way is this point clear like if I give let's say 20 pixel as a
vertical can you see this it's moving down the vertical direction now if I go
and give the blur let's say five pixel can you see this blur how how blur the
shadows becoming blur as much as you add here it will become more blur let's say
if I make 15 to 12 that's that's what it gives your blur effect on the border now
after that what you can give is how long you want to spread this blur let's say if
I make 50 pixel okay how long I want to spread the blur let's say if I
make five pixel okay then actual magic comes this is other properties that you
want can apply on a box shadow but actual properties like color let's say if
I make green and I give something like let's say I select an RGBA this shadow
let's say we reduce this as a one pixel and we make it as two pixel let's say we
make it as like blur as a two pixel let's make blur more eight so that you
have a shadow sort of feel and let's remove border also if you remove border
let's see how magical this box looks like and we can have something like
let's say border radius I don't know if this will be visible since we don't have
border eight pixel so this is what we were doing in the card right we were
adding some shadow to look up do you find this good guys do you find this
good it some bit like it
so this is what we are doing let's say if you want to again spread this hard
gently I give 10 it will move on that X axis to the right if I want to move it
them to the bottom then I can you can use I can use this one so this is one of
the way you can play around with the box shadow but there's another thing that
you can do if you like to fix the box shadow right one of the best ways to go
and do it in the browser itself like let's say I go and open the browser that
is something how I play around with box shadow at my workplace if I want to deal
with this one reason I will tell you why if I go and select this element let's
say this is a card if you see here I have this one whenever I have this
selected right I can select like a how much I need along the X axis or how
much along the y-axis I need or else if I need around this one or if I need on
the center itself and I can give some blur of 8 pixel or how much blur I need
then I can spread it if I need let's say if I want to spread the shadow does this
look cool
yes this this is how you can play around with blur anywhere you want to do it
then there's something called inset it's like inset is also something like if you
want to add a blur inside where you want to play it inside okay let's say you
apply this one and you leave it and you go to the card if you see you if you
want to apply a like shadow inside you have to give the word inset then only
you can play around with that one let's say if I go and do add here
something like inset you see this it's applying the blur inside inside yes yes
yes open so it acts it goes on X axis for axis that's why the first two
values whatever you are giving those are actually meant for horizontal axis
and vertical axis like where you want to move then you have a blur the width of
blur then you can keep like a how like once you define the blur how much spread
I want once that blur is there yeah inside 10 pixel is there like you can
do it now like if I open that again tool so it goes on longer the x-axis y-axis
right let's say if I go on to and the both negative right X is negative and Y
is negative here in diverse like when you go for off in our inset when you go
for off again this is how it works X and Y axis is a bit different here but
generally this this coordinate is something both have used to have
negative isn't it sorry this is the quadrant rightly mentioned coming from
top to bottom I forgot much but I hope this box shadow you are able to relate
how can you revolve and play around with this one cool field right so I hope you
will be play or will be able to play around with box shadow I hope box shadow
is clear for you like how can you deal with it are because by default right
whenever you want to fix it this is whenever you type it down 1 pixel 2
pixel 8 5 or you want to give the color that you won't be able to fix it
right away by writing it you can use inspector what was our last one element
be before the horizontal vertical blur before horizontal this one inset is it
this one 5 pixel spread so let's say if I go and show you real-time use case if
I go and select this one if I spread this let's say this is the 5 pixel this
is the last element if I can't spread it how much how much ever I want let's say
if I make 100% of it it didn't take it but you can take it as much as you want
like how much as you want to increase it here you can apply I guess let's say if
I open here and so in I'll remove this inset I don't need this inset but let's
say I make this 50 pixel can you see this something got it yeah size of
right so I hope this property is clear I have one last topic guys to cover in
CSS which is different types of units right different types of units dot
let's take this way html5 so I want you guys to tell me how many units you have
seen or you we have used it till now
case I'd say okay pixel the fraction it is specific to grid somewhere so
percentage then view height and then view width also I can include which is
W view then something is let's say this is view height then these are the fixed
units these are the something called as let's say absolute units whereas do you
know this there is a there are something like centimeter millimeter inch this can
be also applied but we don't really use them then you have something like the
relative units inside it related units two of the most used things one would be
you would be playing around with them is something called relative M the so the
you you pronounce this one as a relative capital M or or else you have something
like M just like M okay now we'll try to explore each of them let's say I create
let me have this open okay we'll go in reverse order itself guys so we'd go in
reverse order let's have a div okay and let's say this is a class of container
and let's say I have something like diff this is lorem 20 okay now this is let's
say again a diff this is also lorem 20 okay so what I did is like I just had
let's say ID as item one let's say this is an ID called as item two let's explore
using this to ice and create a style block okay so what I'll do is like I'll
use this class container and I'll use something like font font size let's say
I use 20 pixel okay now firstly everything inheritance so font as I've
told you earlier that font can be like inherited so everything went into this
one okay but I'll go and say that hashtag item to as a font size to be
eight pixel so this is specific whenever you say pixel you are trying to use a
specific let's say like each screen is built using like some range of pixels
guys let's say even if you go and try to see here right let's say if I select the
whole body everything will be having in terms of like pixel size 880 into 240
that is what my pixel is okay every screen will have its own respective
pixels so now that's how the space units works for them like that's how your
screens are decided but now what I did is like I've selected hey any screen you
pick it up any screen doesn't matter how big screen is how less screen is size in
my leg doesn't matter I'll pick it 10 pixel of that screen size is this clear
what when we say pixel when we use PX what does it exactly mean now let's say
I use something like item one now I say font size and I say something like let's
say to EM what just happened is what just happened when I used to EM the
font size you know increased at least this thing I can say the font is
increased for this particular content now let's see open in live server open
in live server
let's debug this one what is the font size of this content when I say to EM
it is showing as a to EM itself it's not showing me the exact value okay because
it has overridden this one but what does this exactly let's say now if I convert
this to EM just remember the difference is this is like this is how it is
looking I'll go and do 40 pixel to fill it is still same size if I write down
40 pixel or 2m how many of you agree guys a few more thumbs up if you are
agreeing that to 2m and 40 pixel are equal so whenever we are using relative
units whenever I'm saying when we say that relative units it's respect to its
parent so if you go and see here item one is wrapped inside this container and
container is having some font as 20 pixel 20 pixel now I'm saying that
whatever I'm writing it in terms of M it is a multiplier of that pixel so
whenever I say to a to it's equal to 20 into 240 pixel let's say if I make it 10
right let's say if I make it 10 it will become 20 pixel if I make it 15 if you
see I'm changing this container height but the content inside content is
getting multiplied are you able to understand now how does M works M
always try to connect with its parent font sizes and it multiplies like this
is a multiplier or let's say you might be seeing that 1.3 1.4 right mostly
people write in the multiple units this way but it just like it behind the
scene what's happening here is that just let me write it on the top so what's
happening is 1.4 into 18 pixel is what is being applied okay I hope this point
is clear how M works now then there is something called as rem now let's see
what if contain what if it not given to contain what by default it will take
okay let's say I comment this thing is I comment this thing I commented this
thing by default 1.4 M is taking something let's say I make it one guys
for easy understanding right I made it one now if I go back in the browser if
you see one M is applied now one M is generally talking about like 16 pixels
guys by default the content comes at 16 let's say if I convert this into 16
pixel just remember this one how it is looking this is how it is looking if I
convert into 16 pixel does it look same Kabir so by default the font let's say
if it container is not there it will go and check in the browser level what is
the font size you have given so it will go and check like take it as 16 but if
you have defined in the parent container it will take with respect to that one
now let's say I convert 10 pixel into 10 rem now this has become really huge
then actually how does the rem works is like it always takes with respect to
browser's default or whatever you have defined in HTML let's say if I go in
HTML since it's 10 rem I'll go and say font pixel as a 2 pixel if I want to
make both the paragraphs equal if I have 10 let's say if I make 1.8 pixel so it
will be equal both are being applied 18 pixel so how this is working is how this
is working is like whenever you use rem it always checks with the HTML content
or the top level like hit exactly HTML itself if I would say there is no
specifically mentioned by default this each rem is equal to 16 pixel okay by
default by default rem or em is equal to 16 pixel if we are giving one unit
but if there is something mentioned rem always prefer HTML tag fonts okay if not
there by default it will go for 16 but whereas come to M checks in hierarchy
for parents if not available it will also take 16 is this point here guys
like how rem works and how em works firstly anyone having any challenge here
understanding these two things guys if there's someone who don't understand it
okay somebody says no face let's say what I'm saying is that rem is then rem is
always good prefer go and this is a multiplier guys whenever I'm saying the
relative units it is trying to multiply with some values so by default if there
is no property in HTML mentioned this 10 pixel will be multiplied by 16 pixel
because that is what browser is giving like a default font size would be 16
pixel that is what I have written here by default rem or em will have a
multiplier of 16 okay let's say multiplier of 16 because it's a default
is 16 okay great okay sorry my mistake what's the best to use what would you
think Hemangi what's the best for you if you have worked on projects what is the
best thing is used if I have written pixel right in any PR if I used PX in
any PR of my experience I've always needed to convert into rem do you know
why rem no not Hemangi em we don't use it we use rem mostly as per my experience
I have used rem I'll tell you why I'll tell you why so if you go and see for
the bigger projects any bigger projects you'll have something like theme file
have anyone seen it like theme file or initial font size like whatever your UX
team gives right you have a default fonts like for paragraph in our
application this would be the font size for the headers this would be the font
size for sight lines this would be a font size so if we have a predefined style
like if you go in a PayPal app or any app let's say Flipkart all the fonts are
like similar in nature if you see paragraph they will been similar in
nature at one place they might not have different right one place they might
not have different so there is a one global file in whole project level or at
org level company level because whole Flipkart app will have a different
teams will be working on each team will have their own specific repo no in each
repo whatever the lead UX team decides right they will give you that what are
the default font sizes now with respect to those font sizes you use a rem unit
and you use as a multiplier to render your content whatever you are particular
project UX team suggest is this clear like why we go with rem units
I hope this point is clear guys and next and if you see other than pixel
percentages we have explored view height and view width are literally same
related to like screen width and screen height like with respect to whatever
viewport is there and we hardly use this I never seen anyone doing this one like
not not used any like literally inch or mmr like cm centimeter millimeter an
inch but I hope you got the basic understanding because people try to
tend to you know face difficulty understanding Rema in EM I think I have
explained that topic so I hope if these things are clear guys content is done
from my side for CSS part I hope you you enjoyed learning like HTML and CSS
because I try to come like take as much concepts I have to but if we have you
know missed anything we'll make a list of it and we'll try to cover in future
also because I'm still here to you for more than four months all right till we
cover a whole full stack right because we learn react and then we learn node
also node JS then express Mongo right all the six so journey is still big
really big but if you face any challenge anything or you're not able to
understand yeah Mongo database thank you so it's no sequel database right so
document DB we'll try to use that but if during this journey you see any CSS at
your office place or any place you're not able to understand let's set
together and explore even the HTML part because I wait I didn't cover some
advance like iframe does anyone know iframe iframe have anyone heard iframe I
see one thumbs up two people no problem uncle no problem
iframe guys YouTube links like how you have like let me show you how does
iframe works it's a really powerful thing but can I start doubt session guys
because I have I've completed the content I'll show you iframe and then we
can keep on discussing if you want but the content is clear do you have any
doubts ember ember is also a framework can you please explain again why did you
use 1.8 pixel to the HTML hey monkey 1.8 pixel in the HTML so these are the like
default like team styles like that was I was referring let's say if your project
says that default font size is 1.8 then you can multiply whatever M you like
rem you want to multiply with so this actually font size will become here 1.8
into 10 which will be equal into 18 pixel this is how it will work is that
clear
okay great so guys I'll start out session then we'll explore iframe so
repeat initial inheritance once in after iframe sure Kabir I'll take that let's
start the doubt session first I'll take our talk one doubt about Kabir like then
we'll go for iframe initial in inheritance okay let's take this example
of this one yeah fourth one let me open this open in the show preview okay no so
Kabir now what happened here is that by this drift tag content by default we are
giving color red if I don't have this part let's say if I cut this the color
red will be applied but if I say that I want by default whatever styles like for
the content itself content like when I say this this particular content that
would be default browser will be given CSS engine whatever default cells keeps
that is like black in color the whenever you want to apply those default colors
you can go for initial okay similarly I think you got confused at anchor tag
let's say if I use anchor tag and I write down something okay and let's say I
href okay if you see in href let's say this is google.com I don't want to click
it it will redirect me there that's how it works but this is by default if you
see coming in blue in color okay but if I use again the style color as initial
I am applying the style for this content inside it not for this whole anchor tag
right if I make it it is coming as a black because the kind whatever this
particular text text will be black in color like same like div or span or
anything you pick is that clear Kabir no it won't take if I if I give to the
color to the body also let's say let's say I pick color and let's say brown it
won't take so this color black color is coming from the browser level
is that clear browser whenever browser is parsing or converting this HTML and
rendering it right then default content color is black some of the CSS you write
some of the CSS by default browser gives you okay I hope this is clear let's go
guys iframe example this is one of the powerful tag so iframe works like this
is not the example that I wanted to show let's say
if you see this example guys what's happening here they used let's say I
copy this one and I use here in the browser
do you see this if you want to like like embed let me yeah embedded is open like
if you want to inject a some like you know different things like a different
projects are a different things so how do I understand iframe right mostly if
you see on a top of your website many times you see advertisements coming up
different things they keep on playing our video audio right they use it iframe
tag like this iframe tag now if you see I can click on it I can it will read
it will like work like a project for me so if you want to inject a new project
inside your project right you can use a iframe tag giving the exact URL where
you can if I use it let's say if I want a browser engine to work in my app I can
simply say www.google.com now just let's say what's happening here this might not
work
okay it needs HTTP yes but it's not loading let's say if I load flipkart
now to the configure it whatever now if you see that flipkart is loading
can you see this case what iframe does if you want to launch a flipkart sort of
app inside your application whatever you have built this is really powerful guys
really powerful I would say like your whole thing will work but the way your
project might not support sometimes but initial load it gives but generally iframes
are used for advertisement or rendering those sort of things are you able to
relate what like iframe example what iframe does it embeds some new project
or new content whatever is designed by giving as a source tag
yeah yeah yeah you can do that you can do that okay so upender has this thing
like and we use embedded is it to embed our projects into portfolio you can
always do that open you can always do that but you have to design your project
such a way that those are like super responsive that it doesn't break
whenever you are using embedded okay so that because you are whenever you embed
it right it will be having such window size because here they have given some
height and width customized so be careful whenever you are injecting in
portfolio you use it this way okay
now I'll show like let's go to the YouTube and show you that one say I
search iframes let's say this they have display none like they aren't using this
one this is they are using now if you see they did something like a sandbox
URL now if you say accounts YouTube what this URL takes to let's say I copy this
URL I click on so this is what they have embedded now if I load it it doesn't
return me anything but I don't know what logic they applied here they're using
for cookies like let's say instead of display none right we'll make a block
in line doesn't show up anything here because even the pages seems to be empty
for us right but what if I gave the same example let's say I pick this source
stack whatever source tag they gave me let's say I pick this source and I
inject in the YouTube so this is the iframe right then instead of display
none I'll I'll say display block and I'll say here
SRC
try
it is not letting me add okay I added this program is now can you see this
guys this this got embedded here because it didn't have height and width now what
if I they disabled height and width here like I mean they were just trying to do
this one maybe a small project they stopped it in YouTube maybe then enable
sometimes like do you remember what used to come here if anyone remembers what
used to come here below this here on the do you remember daughter's go YouTube
daughter's like Google daughters they build different types of things right
this particular YouTube icon get exchange changed with that have you seen
that this icon get changed I believe that's where they were trying to embed
it and override this one because you don't want to deploy it separately maybe
that's how they were using it
okay but anyways guys any more doubts
this class is awesome so excited sure sure copy thank you thank you for
appreciation
we'll keep building cool things ways just I would ask you know keep keep okay
I'll take that somebody give me a minute I'll take that I'll answer now if I use
CSS and use great it's covering the whole page in HTML file but when I use
in same in CSS JS well it's not taking so can you show me the code some bit
because I want to see how you are using like how we are trying to render like
JS how we are connecting I'll see if I once I'll push the code I'll give the
permission okay get commit minus and then class 7 get push let me check if I
can give you an access some bit some bit I have on mute button then if I go for
settings screen share admin hello okay then
give me a minute I'm trying to find that option so me we unmuted okay yeah I
got it so I'm unmuting you you will be able to have that option to share some
you can check that okay no worries can you check that can you check if you are
having access to share the screen
some bit I unmuted you you are on mute can you try to speak once okay speak
once do you see access yeah I have got the access right now okay yeah like I
shared miss okay I'll pull this window here for everyone yeah please share
yeah is my screen visible I don't see your screen being shared now is it
visible no can anyone can anyone see guys I am not able to see that oh is it
I'm not able to see it just a second
like I'm actually not able to see it do do you mind some bit like you can share
me or get a repo I can I can share the screen if you have pushed that code in
get up no I haven't pushed it it's just in my local oh okay can you try to
reshare it once maybe I'll be able to see it yeah I'll do that yeah yeah
shared it
I'm not literally okay I'll just try to you know like tell you the problem
what's happening huh huh yeah please yesterday when we discussed about the
grids right so we like created a layout like head on nav mean so when I try to
do it with a dot HTML file right it's like covering the whole page like how
we were able to see yesterday but if I create like something as a dot thing
right huh as a dot js file huh for the same CSS huh it's like you mean to say
that you you manipulated the extension is it correct yes so that wouldn't work
right if you are trying to play around with something like an HTML files in
HTML like how does browser understand it okay like if you're using dot js
extension it's a code which is to try to render it but it won't be able to pass
the CSS from that that's how extension works extensions like if I if I try to
show it right let me share my screen I'll show you that example like whatever
you are trying to do it let me know if you can see the screen yeah I can right
now this is let's say I pick this HTML I have show preview yeah now let's say I
convert this into js file okay do you see this what just happened yeah that I
understand like this show preview is not working but I am like running it on the
server okay like I connected the CSS to this JS every CSS is working fine only
the width and height are getting affected oh then I think I need to look
at it completely are you can you push that code and I can check and I can let
you know in the whatsapp chat yeah sure I'll do that yeah push that code I can
check that okay if I think you are trying to send HTML from a JS code you
are trying to it's like server-side rendering if I try to space specifically
I'm trying to render the HTML from the server not sure I'll just push it then
maybe I can discuss on that yeah sure sure sure I'll do that yeah yeah thanks a
yeah so I'll mute you back yeah
guys any yeah like there's a one cool website case open the hash shared
earlier also I bookmarked it but if you see this this is something let's say if
I click this if you see this it's a music got play started playing once it
loads it is a 3d website
okay when I click start there's a music can anyone here along with me okay let's
do one thing I'll pin this play in your systems yes play in your systems finally
play in your system and click on the start button stop the music right you
are able to see that music now let's let's say like actually what's happening
this is a really cool site that they built it but what's happening here when
I load this let's say I do it in incognito so that I can see what all
things are happening okay inspect it and I click play load it first it got this
one then you see it is downloading still or else I can say that this is parsing
the content whatever content you have they have shared it is parsing okay if
you see the amount of MBs resource got downloaded okay the amount of MBs that
got downloaded 10 KB per second where 23 24 MB 23 MB of data is transferred
onto the client it for sure this site looks cool because they added loader
there initially okay but if you go and explore this one right what what could
be the thing that they might have done if you see that mp3 where they have
linked let's say if I try to find this way this mp3 is loaded like this music
is coming from or let's do something let's do something this is the code
that they have it right let's say I have a start button this is start button is
it button start here now whenever you click this button they that but let it
start loading it now they have use position fixed inline cells that are
fine but on click of this button there should be something happening so if I go
into the JS part where is the JS code or else let's say if I can debug this one
okay I didn't go through that one but one thing I would unappreciate this
website is actually a sound would you won't be able to find this one sound
footer sound yeah sound labels and everything is there that's that's cool
site but one thing I have only one issue right guys here is that the amount of
resource if you see twenty nine point three MB data transfer right do you see
this twenty nine twenty nine point three MB of data that is received firstly let's
go pick any website let's pick any big website that you want let's go and
amazon.com just see how much of data is transferred for me to reach this
particular site okay since I'm doing from incognito it asked me to enter
this PCC EAN let's I clear this again I continue shopping okay it loaded with a
whole website but if you see for the whole Amazon level of content it it got
only downloaded 4.6 MB of data that big huge website let's go and open YouTube
okay YouTube being the biggest streaming service content right let's say I go to
YouTube now see when I'm playing YouTube imagine YouTube got loaded with only
2.1 MB 2.1 MB guys imagine if you see the amount of requests are going the
things now but if you go and load this website for the initial load you are
trying to download 29 MB at the speed of 10.7 KB so that load time if you see the
load time here it takes it took 9.1 seconds to load the website whereas if
you go for YouTube it took 1.5 second for Amazon it took 3.5 second because I
had to enter that key all else it would be speed now which website you would
prefer guys let's say you are on Instagram you have one reel and it got
stuck for one second or two second would you state that or you would move to the
next reel
next right so in industry right in industry one of the basic norm one of
the basic norm is that hey your content right your content whatever the content
you are having firstly you have to consider two things first is once you
build since I didn't introduce Dom imagine once your Dom is built right
then the painting starts happening on the site so the Dom content load this is
most important parameter this parameter of load 3.5 seconds is might be loading
JavaScript and every other thing it will be kept on loading the code that's fine
but this thing matters more let's go and see it for this site what they have
done it is taking 5.7 seconds now if you go and do that performance testing right
for this website let's say I do this one profiling
since it is already downloaded it might not download because it is cached okay
but you will able to analyze the results here which will show that hey it is
taking more amount of time and everything okay but one of the best
thing is to do is lighthouse testing has anyone done it this one lighthouse
testing
so this test this is like on a chrome if you want to test your any website you
want to test its performance or accessibility best practices you can go
to lighthouse and analyze the page load let's say if I do analyze the page load
it will be audit that whole website it will audit that website and it will test
and let you know that how you can improve your website let's say it is
downloading the whole content again see if it says if the site takes more than
one second so it will give you the all the speeds and it will compare it will
do the all the analytics and give you the results of your website whether your
website is good enough or wrong it's a really cool project I hats off to them
who have built it and they have done only one server side render projected
everything into one file of HTML that's where it hit me hard if they wouldn't
have that only one thing right if they had lazy loading sort of concept if you
see performance got hit all the other parameters are really great but if their
engineers have decided that we'll take a hit on a performance then you should
see if I go and a YouTube okay I go and do it on a YouTube let's say I select a
SEO progressive web app also and like the speed
let's see how fast what results this YouTube gives us
this is taking time to do it but you can experiment on your on your things guys
go do it on your projects that you are building or talk to them like how can
you improve it or what you can do it right talk to them if you see YouTube
performance got hit drastically okay they now the best thing right the best
thing what they can do what this lighthouse gives you it gives you a few
parameters these are the once you become higher level of engineering in front end
right this is somewhere you will come and fix the issues like first content
full paint total blocking time I'll talk about this parameter step by step but
not now but if you come to this website let's say first let's say their time
what is the most time of the most time spent first content full paint is 2.8
seconds for the YouTube it is 2.3 seconds okay this parameter should be as much
slow as possible and you will get you can calculate everything right you will
get so you'll see that all the things that you are getting if you they are
pointing out something called index TV now if you go into the application and
there is something called index TV they are having too much of data stored
guys and therefore this one okay for the YouTube for like percent entities to you
can or do play around with this data I'm doing it so this is in incognito mode
this is the performance but if I do it for the YouTube again in the normal
browser right it will load it faster rate because they have all the data
cached it need not to download again we'll explore this DB also like once we
go in the JS part like all the DBS that are given here
it's too much we have discussed so let's close the session today we'll come back
on Thursday where we'll start JavaScript and we'll explore further but I would
ask you guys you know to complete your assignments and do whatever problems
you face let me know okay we'll explore that okay some with I'll I'll mark your
question as answered as of now but I'll pick it off line okay
so nobody's that can we close the session guys today for today final thumbs
up cell and see you in the next class guys hope you do your assignments
good night guys take care bye guys
thank you Kendra good night
you